<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The religion of an oath a discourse proving the danger and immorality of rash and prophane swearing / by the late reverend and judicious Dr. Claggett.</title>
            <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37673</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16999919</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16999919</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105688</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33217)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105688)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1611:62)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The religion of an oath a discourse proving the danger and immorality of rash and prophane swearing / by the late reverend and judicious Dr. Claggett.</title>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Reprinted on occasion of the Parliament's address to His Majesty to issue out his proclamation against immorality &amp;c."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swearing.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105688:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Religion of an Oath.</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE, PROVING <hi>The</hi> Danger <hi>and</hi> Immorality OF <hi>Raſh</hi> and <hi>Prophane Swearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the late Reverend and Judicious Dr. <hi>Claggett.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reprinted on Occaſion of the Parliament's Addreſs to His Majeſty to Iſſue out His Proclamation againſt Immorality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105688:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105688:2"/>
            <head>THE Religion of an OATH, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. V. 34, 35, 36, 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But I ſay unto you, Swear not at all; neither by heaven, for it is God's throne: nor by the earth, for it is his footſtool: neither by Jeruſalem, for it is the City of the great King. Neither ſhalt thou ſwear by thy head, becauſe thou canſt not make one hair white or black. But let your communication be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay: for whatſoever is more than this, cometh of evil.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THat Religion and the fear of God, and a ſenſe of his Authority, are Principles ſuppoſed by the Laws of God, is from hence evident, that in great part the proceſs of our Courts depends upon Teſtimony given under the obligation of an Oath; for though the uſe of an Oath there, is required by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authority; yet the peculiar obligation it lays upon us to ſpeak the Truth, is antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all Humane Laws, being founded ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally upon our Duty to God: Wherefore though an Oath in reſpect of ſome uſe and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105688:3"/>end of it, may be a Civil Act, yet in reſpect of the reaſon whereby it obligeth, it is an Act of Religion; for this reaſon it is highly conducible to the end of Civil Government, to maintain a ſenſe of Religion in the minds of men; and particularly it muſt be of great uſe to make them obſerve thoſe Laws of God, which are plainly deſigned to ſecure the reverence which is due to an Oath, and to keep men at a wide diſtance from the danger of Perjury: Such is that Law of our Saviour, which I have read to you, which therefore doth not tend more to the Honour of God, than to the Common Good of Mankind; and this no man can be ignorant of, who conſiders what a vaſt influence the uſe of an Oath hath upon all the Affairs of Humane Life. This is that whereby we come to conſide in one another about things of the greateſt moment to our lives; this is that which is ſo often neceſſary to ſecure our Properties, to ſave us from wrong, and to make even our Enemy to do us right; it is this which all Proceſſes in Courts of Judicature are governed by, which is ſuppoſed to all Adminiſtrations of Juſtice, and gives an end to all Controverſies about matters of Fact, which will be no otherways decided; it is this which muſt either direct or miſguide the wiſeſt Magiſtrates, and make their Sentence it ſelf either right or wrong; and by which we are either ſtrongly guarded againſt Injury, or almoſt inevitably expoſed to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105688:3"/>it. Of how great conſequence therefore muſt it be to the good of all men, to have the reverence of an Oath ſecured, and to make every man tremble at the thought of Perjury, ſince the World cannot be well-governed, nor the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations of Juſtice go forward, without the uſe of Oaths? And yet we had better be without them, in as many caſes as there are wherein Men are not afraid to be Forſworn. And yet alas! it is the daily complaint of our Age, That the fear of an Oath is almoſt baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the World: And although it be really a thouſand times more dreadful to profane the Name of God, by calling him to be a witneſs to our Lies, than it would be to play before the Mouth of a Cannon while it was Firing; yet, if we may believe the Reports which are ſometimes made from Courts of Judicature, there are very few Peaſants ſo puſillanimous but they are hardy enough to Swear to any thing; and with equal confidence to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict one another in the plaineſt matters, and when under an equal obligation to ſpeak the Truth, by the Invocation of the dreadful Name of God. Now if we would enquire how the ſacredneſs of an Oath is grown into ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, I do not queſtion but the common and frequent uſe of Swearing in our ordinary Converſation, would be found at leaſt acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to that diſhonour which is done to God, and that miſchief to men by the ſo frequent Perjuries of our Age. Oaths are grown ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105688:4"/>familiar with us, that men have forgotten the nature and true uſe of them, and are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that they call the Divine Vengeance upon themſelves, if their Teſtimonies be not exactly true; they have been proſtituted to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Services, and profan'd by common uſe; and then no wonder if the Sacred Obligation peculiar to them be forgotten, when they are uſed in thoſe ſpecial caſes for which they ought to be reſerved; therefore if we would do any thing to recover the fear of an Oath amongſt our Country-men, we muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do it by means contrary to thoſe whereby it hath been ſo generally loſt, that is, By abſtaining our ſelves, and not only ſo, but by diſſuading and reſtraining others as much as in us lies, from that familiar and faſhiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Swearing which is one of the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of our Age; to which end I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to explain the meaning and reaſon of theſe words of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>And in them I ſhall conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Law it ſelf, <hi>Swear not at all; but let your communication be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſanction and reaſon of this Law, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The Authority of our Saviour, <hi>But I ſay unto you.</hi> 2. The nature of the thing it ſelf, <hi>For whatſoever is more than this, cometh of evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Law it ſelf we are to conſider the Prohibition, and the Precept.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Prohibition; which contains,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105688:4"/> 1. A general Rule, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Some particular inſtances whereto the Rule extends, <hi>Neither by Heaven, nor by Earth, nor by Jeruſalem, nor by thy head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Reaſon why the Rule extends to theſe Inſtances; not by Heaven, <hi>for it is God's Throne;</hi> not by the Earth, <hi>for it is his footſtool;</hi> not by <hi>Jeruſalem, for it is the City of the great King;</hi> not by thy Head, <hi>for thou canſt not make one hair white or black.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us begin with the general Rule, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> From which words the Anabaptiſts and Quakers have contended, That an Oath, or an Appeal to God that what we ſay is true, is in no caſe lawful: I ſhall here ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and prove, that the meaning of the Rule is this, That we are not to Swear in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and daily Converſation with Men; and this will appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By comparing the Prohibition with the Precept.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With the particular inſtances whereunto the Prohibition extends.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With the Precept, <hi>But let your communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay, (i. e.)</hi> Let this be the manner of your ordinary diſcourſe, barely to affirm or deny, or if need be, ſometimes with vehemence, which perhaps is intimated by the repetition of <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is plain, if this be the ſenſe of the Precept, that the Prohibition doth not extend to Caſes which belong not to the common and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105688:5"/>ordinary Converſation of Men, ſuch as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding of Controverſies for the ſecurity of the publick peace; the aſſuring of fidelity to the Government, and the ratifying of Leagues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are caſes properly excepted from this Rule of an uſual and ordinary communication with each other, becauſe they are no part thereof: But I confeſs, I do not lay the ſtreſs of the proof upon this Argument only, but on this, together with the ſecond, which is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon comparing the general Rule with the particular inſtances, whereby the uſe of it is explained, <hi>neither by Heaven, for it is God's Throne, &amp;c.</hi> Our Saviour's deſign in theſe words cannot be better underſtood, than by conſidering what thoſe corrupt Principles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matter of Swearing were, which had crept in among the <hi>Jews;</hi> and firſt, as their own Authors tell us, it was generally held amongſt them, that they ought not to Swear by the Name of God in light and trivial Caſes, but they believed it was no Sin to Swear upon any occaſion by a Creature that was a remarkable inſtance of God's Favour and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, as <hi>by Heaven,</hi> or <hi>by the Earth,</hi> or <hi>by Jeruſalem,</hi> or <hi>by their Head,</hi> which are the Inſtances here noted by our Saviour. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome of them, and particularly the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi> taught, that the Guilt of Perjury was not incurr'd, when a falſhood was atteſted by theſe kind of Oaths, excepting only in the Caſes of Swearing <hi>by the Gold of the Temple, and the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105688:5"/>Gift upon the Altar;</hi> by which Oaths they acknowledged themſelves to be bound, as we find <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>(i.e.)</hi> either to ſpeak the Truth, or to the Penalty of Falſe-Swearing: Hence, I ſay, that our Saviour's words, <hi>Swear not all, neither by Heaven, &amp;c.</hi> being ſpoken to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who well enough underſtood the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practiſes of their Countreymen in this matter, could not reaſonably be thought to have any other meaning than this, That they ought not to Swear by the Creatures of God in any of thoſe Caſes wherein it is unlawful to Swear by the Almighty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> in their uſual Communication with one another: For it ſeems the <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were not arrived to that inſolence, which it is ſo dreadful to think that Chriſtians now-a-days ſhould not ſcruple, of profaning the Name of the Moſt High God, by calling him at every turn to be Witneſs of their talk: And therefore our Saviour found it needleſs to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them Swearing by his Name, for they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready believed that to be an impious thing; but he tells them, they muſt neither Swear <hi>by Heaven,</hi> nor by any thing elſe; as if he had ſaid, You have been allowed to liberty of Swearing as oft as you pleaſe, provided you do not uſe the Name of God himſelf; it is ordinary with you to Swear by Heaven, and Earth, and by the Temple, and your Lives and Souls, and that in thoſe Caſes wherein you rightly believe it would be a profane rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105688:6"/>to invoke the Majeſty of God directly; <hi>But I ſay unto you, Swear not at all;</hi> you ſhall not henceforth take the liberty of uſing any kind of Oaths in thoſe Caſes wherein you are not to appeal to God himſelf; but upon all theſe occaſions, whatever you aſſert, or whatever you promiſe, uſe the ſimplicity and plainneſs of ſome affirmation or denial. And thus our Saviour reſtrained the licentiouſneſs of thoſe common Swearers, that thought they might ſafely Swear <hi>by Heaven,</hi> and uſe the like Oaths at any time, and upon any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and withal corrected that abuſe which the Doctrine of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> had brought into this Practice, <hi>viz.</hi> That Men were not lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the guilt of Perjury by ſuch Oaths as theſe were; which I ſhall more diſtinctly ſhew under the third Head. The meaning then of our Saviour's Prohibition is not this, That it is unlawful at any time to Swear by the Name of God; but that it is unlawful to Swear by any Creature in any Caſe, wherein it would be ſo to appeal directly to the Knowledge and Juſtice of God himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to thoſe Inſtances by which the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rule is explained, it is obſerveable,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Swearing by any of the Creatures is forbidden, not only by <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> which with the reſt are particularly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by our Saviour, becauſe theſe forms of Swearing were moſt in uſe amongſt the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105688:6"/> 2. We are to note, that our Saviour calls it <hi>Swearing,</hi> to uſe theſe forms of Speech in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting what we ſay; they are not ſo many words loſt, as we may be inclined to think, but we bring upon our ſelves the obligation of an Oath, by the uſing of them, as ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently appear. If indeed any ways of ſpeaking have obtained amongſt us, which look like Swearing, but are not, being altogether unapt to excite any Thought of Divine Juſtice, I do not queſtion, but they are to be laid aſide too, becauſe ſurely the Prohibition of Swearing at all, excludes not only all real, but all broken, apiſh and inſignificant Oaths; but if it were not ſo, one would think that a ſmall meaſure of Sobriety and Wiſdom ſhould keep a man from debaſing and vilifying the acknowledged forms of ſpeaking that are peculiar to Oaths, by applying them to ſuch ſenſleſs ſounds, as make them to ſignify nothing; 'Tis a good Rule which a wiſe man hath given, That all forms, beſides thoſe wherein there is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate appeal to God, are better avoided when there is need of Swearing; and when there is no need, we ſhould not Swear at all, neither by Heaven, nor by any thing elſe. Let us now conſider,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Reaſons why the Prohibition extends to theſe inſtances, and the like, Not <hi>by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for it is God's Throne; and he that ſweareth by Heaven, ſweareth by the Throne of God, and him that ſitteth thereon,</hi> Matth. 23. Not <hi>by the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105688:7"/>Earth, for it is his footſtool;</hi> it is a remarkable ſubject of his Providence; and to Swear hereby, is in effect all one as to appeal to God that upholds it by his Power: Not <hi>by Jeruſalem,</hi> nor any holy place that hath a peculiar relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God, for the ſame reaſon; nor <hi>by thy head, for thou canſt not make one hair white or black, (i. e.)</hi> thou haſt no power over thy life, and art ſo unable to ſubſiſt independently upon God, that thou canſt not ſo much as alter the colour of thine Hair: Now ſince thy Head, thy Life and Safety, depends upon the Divine Providence, to Swear by thy Head, and by thy Life, and conſequently by thy hope of Life and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is indeed to Swear by him upon whom thou dependeſt for thy life, and who only hath all power to ſave and to deſtroy; ſo that the general reaſon why theſe Oaths are to be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is becauſe they are equivalent to formal Swearing by the Creator of all things, and contrary to the Opinion of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> brought an equal Obligation upon him that uſed them, with Swearing downright by our Maker: Now they acknowledged, that Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directly by the Name of God, and where that was uſed, was not lawful in their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary occaſions of ſpeaking; our Saviour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds upon this ſuppoſition, and infers, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not lawful to uſe thoſe other Oaths upon thoſe occaſions, becauſe they implied an appeal to the Juſtice and the Omnipreſence of God himſelf. And thus I have endeavoured to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105688:7"/>explain the Prohibition contained in this Law of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>As for the Precept, <hi>But let your communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay;</hi> it needs no farther inquiry into the ſenſe of it, the plain meaning of them already appearing to be this: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelves with bare affirming and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatever you have occaſion to ſpeak of, without adding thereto any kind of Oaths and Imprecations.</p>
            <p>And thus much concerning the Law it ſelf, which one would think were as eaſy to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as it is to be underſtood; and certainly it is great pity that any man ſhould need much perſuaſion to keep it; but if it ſhould be ſo, we do not want Arguments clear and ſtrong enough to prevail with any conſidering Perſon; and theſe are contained in the Sanction of this Law; which is the ſecond thing I am to ſpeak to, and which I have already told you is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon the Authority of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon the Reaſon of the Law itſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Authority of our Saviour, who eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed this Law by theſe words, <hi>But I ſay unto you.</hi> I do not find any ſuch expreſs Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Swearing in ordinary Converſation as this, before our Saviour's time; not but that I think the unlawfulneſs of that liberty which here he abridgeth his Diſciples of, might by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105688:8"/>good conſequence be inferred from the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets; but what need we look for any other Rule in this matter beſides this, which is ſo plain and expreſs, and which we have received from the Son of God himſelf? There can now be no diſpute, whether we may lawfully Swear in thoſe Caſes wherein an Oath is needleſs; for our Lord's Command is ſo full againſt it, that a queſtion hath been made, though upon no juſt ground, Whether it be lawful for a Chriſtian to Swear at all? Now if the ſenſe of our Saviour's Authority can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with us to do any thing in obedience to him, it will not fail to govern us in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where the performance of his Will is ſo eaſy, and the violation of it is not rewarded by any gain or pleaſure, nor ſollicited by any Temptation that can faſten upon our ſenſual Luſts and Appetites; nor can be reſolved eaſily into any other Cauſe, but a Spirit of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the Goſpel of our Lord; which may make us aſtoniſhed, that in an Age pretending to the Worſhip of God, in a Nation formed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Chriſtian Church, ſo many ſhould be found of almoſt all Qualities and Degrees, who bid defiance to the Authority of our Saviour, by refuſing to make ſo ſmall an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, as the keeping of a Law ſo eaſy as this; that we ſhould thus put into our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe a peculiar Character, to let the World know, that we are no Chriſtians, though we were Baptized into the Name of Chriſt; leſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105688:8"/>it ſhould not be obſerved by our practices, that we ſhould take care to diſcover it by our language, that we are none of thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Jeſus to be the Son of God: If we had no other reaſon, but the Will of our Lord and Saviour to rule us in this matter, that certainly ſhould be enough to conclude us; he that ſhould want a farther obligation, deſerves to be ranked with Heathens and Infidels; and yet the thing which our Saviour here forbids, is evil in it ſelf too, and contains many foul and deteſtable Immoralities in its own nature; and therefore the common Swearer's Sin, how enormous muſt it needs be, who refuſeth to do a very ſmall matter to avoid ſo great a guilt! That the heinouſneſs whereof may yet farther appear, I ſhall proceed to the</p>
            <p>Second Conſideration under this Head, <hi>viz.</hi> The Reaſon of the Law it ſelf, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in theſe words, Whatſoever is more than the plainneſs of affirmation and denial in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſcourſe, <hi>cometh of evil;</hi> I will therefore endeavour theſe two following things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To make it appear what thoſe evil diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions are which this practice implies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To examine the pretences that are only poſſible to be alledged in excuſe of it. Now if men are led to it by no good Principle; if the diſpoſitions thereunto are wholly evil; if evil be implied in the very pretences brought to excuſe it; nothing can be farther deſired to demonſtrate that this is to be concluded, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105688:9"/>That it is an Immorality to Swear in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; and whatſoever is more than that ſimplicity of Language which our Saviour's Rule confines us to, <hi>cometh of evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The true Principles and Cauſes inclining men to this practice, are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Want of Reverence towards God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Careleſneſs of avoiding the Crime of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Immodeſty and Pride.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Lightneſs and vanity of mind. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there muſt be all theſe things together to make up a common Swearer; for if he either had reverent Thoughts of God, or feared to be Forſworn; or if he had but a little modeſty and good manners, or any tolerable meaſure of a ſteddy and ſerious ſpirit, any one of theſe things would ſecure him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Cuſtomary Swearing betrays great irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence towards God; for unleſs a man had very mean and diſhonourable Thoughts of God, how durſt he make ſo bold with him, as to affirm nothing ſo ſilly, and tranſact nothing ſo trivial and mean, but he muſt ſummon God to be his Witneſs? Reverence of the Deity is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways expreſſed by ſeparating holy things from vile and common uſes; and becauſe an Oath is an appeal to the Knowledge and Juſtice of God, it is greater rudeneſs to preſs it to unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Services, than it would be for the meaneſt of People to call the King out of his Throne to hear every idle Tale they brought
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105688:9"/>againſt one another. If an Oath be an holy thing, let us uſe it as we do thoſe holy places, which we do not put to all Imployments, but reſerve them for their peculiar uſe. What a contempt of Religion would it be for men to bring their Markets into the Houſe of God, and pretend to ſanctify their worldly Affairs and Pleaſures, by tranſacting them in the place of his Worſhip? I do not ſee but 'tis altogether as irreligious to mix our talk with Oaths upon every occaſion; for hereby we make as cheap with God, as by proſtituting any other Sacred thing to a common and trivial uſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It argues a man not to fear that horrid Crime of Perjury; for if he were afraid of it, how cautious and deliberate would he be, e're he ventured to affirm any thing upon Oath? He would conſider whether it were exactly true, whether it were certain, or only proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; whether he was not liable to miſtake, or miſinformation, in the caſe, and many other things which are often neceſſary to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſideration with that man that trembles at the thought of Perjury; but the light is not more clear at mid-day, than that common Swearers trouble themſelves with none of theſe Thoughts; what they ſay at a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they boldly Swear; what they raſhly utter, they as raſhly add Oaths and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to; their habit of Swearing makes them not one jot the more wary in their talk; and the ſlipperineſs of their Tongues, not at all the more afraid of an Oath; which is a plain Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105688:10"/>that they have little apprehenſion of Perjury, and are not afraid to be Forſworn; for I ſay, Did we ever find that thoſe who are given to Swearing, are more deliberate and ſlow to ſpeak than other men? Do they weigh their words with more exactneſs? Do they refrain from looſneſs of talk, and diſſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mirth and Jollity more than thoſe who are content to ſpeak upon their honeſt word? No, but on the contrary, they are uſually more free and prodigal of their diſcourſe; their words are guided with leſs conſideration and judgment, and their Tongues hang more looſly in their Heads than is obſervable in other men; nay, it is well known, that they are then moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful of their Oaths, when they are leaſt able to govern their talk with diſcretion, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> when they are drunk either with Wine or Paſſion; and what numerous Perjuries then in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood are theſe men guilty of! nay, it is not improbable but ſome of them may be For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn every day they riſe; for though men may pleaſe themſelves with thinking that they do but ſwear in jeſt, yet the obligation of an Oath is not to be laughed away; when men ſwear they will do this or that, which it may be they intend not at all; or that ſuch a thing is true, which they know is falſe, they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs guilty of Perjury, for not minding that they are ſo, ſince a Sin ceaſeth not to be what it is, meerly by the ſtupidity of a man's Confcience; but all that can be ſaid in this caſe is, That they are not apprehenſive of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105688:10"/>guilt, nor afraid of the crime of Perjury, which is that Immorality that I charge the common Swearer withal; and this St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of, that the reaſon which he aſſigns why our Saviour prohibited unneceſſary Oaths, was this, <hi>ne perjuri ſmus,</hi> leſt we ſhould be forſworn, which every man is in apparent danger of, who promiſcuouſly adds Oaths to his Talk, as I have already noted. And doubtleſs he that refuſeth to ſecure himſelf from Perjury that way which our Saviour hath preſcribed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares plainly enough that he is not ſo careful againſt it, as a due ſenſe of the foulneſs of that Sin would make him. That in the buſneſs of an Oath men are obliged to proceed with great care and deliberation, is a thing ſo plain, that I ſhould be aſhamed to go about the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it: And I am confident, if men would tye themſelves to weigh the Truth of every thing they affirmed, before they would venture to Swear to it, they would ſpare a great many of their Oaths; and if they found it were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly true, they would be immediately ſenſible, that it deſerved not ſo ſolemn a confirmation, and be aſhamed of the vanity of doing ſo great a thing to no purpoſe; which is a conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that I ſhall by and by more particularly offer. In the mean time,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Needleſs Swearing argues Immodeſty and Pride, and an arrogant ſpirit. Few things are more unſeemly in a man, than to affirm every thing with confidence, and to be peremptory in all his talk, for this is to impoſe upon his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105688:11"/>Company, and leave no room for any body to be of another mind; and ſuch Companions are ſhunned by all wiſe Perſons, as being void of that modeſty and ſobriety which make men ſociable and converſible; but what ſhall we ſay to thoſe who are not only poſitive and dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical in their common diſcourſe, but aſſert every thing almoſt which they ſay, upon Oath? Certainly in this kind of Behaviour there is as much ill Manners towards men, as there is rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards God; for what greater inſtance can be given of an imperious and a peremptory temper, than to ſeal our talk with Oaths, and leave no room for another to doubt of what we ſay, under the pain of accuſing us of Perjury? A modeſt and wiſe man, when he delivers his judgment in many things, where poſſibly he might, without fear of being accuſed of Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, be peremptory and concluſive, yet chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to declare himſelf with that reſervedneſs, as may invite another man to ſhew all his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the contrary, without fear of diſpleaſing him; and this we all know is a great Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any man's Converſation, and of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe to maintain peace, and good will, and good correſpondence in all Societies; But light is not more contrary to darkneſs, than the cuſtom of Swearing is to this human and gentle temper; wherefore it betrays immodeſty and arrogance.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it proceeds alſo from great vanity and lightneſs of ſpirit, which appears in theſe two plain inſtances of it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105688:11"/>
            <p> The firſt is, in making no difference between matters of ſerious importance and conſideration, and ſuch as are frivolous, and of little conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; in treating thoſe with the ſame ſpirit and behaviour, that are ſuitable only to theſe, which is an undoubted argument of childiſhneſs, and a frothy mind; this is that which the Swearer is apparently chargeable with; for otherwiſe how could he in the ſame light hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, wherein he is delivering ſomething to make the Company laugh, preſume to prophane ſo ſacred a thing as an Oath is, by accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a poor ſilly Jeſt with it? Does the taking of an Oath require no more ſeriouſneſs than is neceſſary to the telling of a Tale? Or can it be fit to tye ſo grave a thing to a ſentence, which if it were written down, would within an hour after, perhaps, appear hatefully ridiculous? And yet nothing is more common with thoſe that allow themſelves in this Sin.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is an Argument of vanity to take more pains for the confirming of what we ſay, than the thing doth at all deſerve. It is plain, that the greateſt part of our Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with one another by diſcourſe and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence, doth not require any ſolemn con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the truth of our words; much leſs the Teſtimony of an Oath; which being the greateſt ſecurity we can give, he muſt be a very light-headed Companion that will throw it away at every turn, who cannot tell what was done yeſterday, or make a Promiſe to his Friend or Acquaintance about the ordinarieſt matter,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105688:12"/>but out comes an Oath, or a Curſe, to bind his words withal: Methinks I could convince any man of ordinary ſenſe, that there is that levity and madneſs implied in this cuſtom, which if it were but ſeen in other things, would bring a man within the danger of <hi>Bedlam;</hi> for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a man were to make a Promiſe to his Friend of that kind which ordinarily happens in our Converſation, as that he would give him a Viſit, or a Meeting where he ſhould appoint, but for the preſent would not ſuffer him to go, till he had gotten an hundred of his Neighbours together to be Witneſſes of his Promiſe; what a ridiculous Fancy would this be? And if a man ſhould ordinarily do thus, he were likely enough to be begg'd, if any thing were to be gotten by it; for nothing is more plain, than that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary aſſurance of a man's word is ſufficient for theſe matters, and will either paſs for them, or he had as good be baniſhed out of human Society, or ſent to ſome other place at leaſt, where being not ſo well known, he may be the better truſted; but 'tis as clear as when the Sun ſhines, that he that will not make ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe under an Oath, nor let his Word go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out calling God to witneſs it, by invoking his Juſtice and Vengeance if he falſifies, (for that's the meaning of an Oath) he does really ten thouſand times more to confirm his Promiſe, than if he had ſummoned Town and Countrey together, than if he had gotten all Mankind, nay, and all the Angels in Heaven together to be Witneſſes between him and his Neighbour.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105688:12"/>Can there readily be a more ridiculous vanity thought of than this, to give away the beſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity I can afford of my fidelity, upon every trifle? I wiſh all thoſe who have been guilty of this Sin, would ſo endeavour after an ordinary Reputation amongſt men, as to be aſhamed of it for the future.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhown what thoſe evil Principles are from whence Swearing in ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation proceeds. It comes of irreverence towards God, careleſneſs of being Forſworn, Immodeſty and Arrogance, Lightneſs and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſpirit; that is to ſay, if a man hath ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fear of God, or a deteſtation of Perjury, or Modeſty, and good Manners, or any Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Seriouſneſs, any one of theſe things will be ſufficient to keep him from uſing need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Oaths, and therefore the common Swearer is deſtitute of them all; and conſequently it muſt needs be a foul Immorality, which groweth out of a Complexion of all thoſe evil Principles that are contrary to theſe good and virtuous diſpoſitions.</p>
            <p>I am in the</p>
            <p>Second place, to examine the pretences that are only poſſible to be alledged in the excuſe, or for the mitigation of this Crime; and if I can ſhew, that evil is implied in theſe alſo, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion will yet be more evident, That whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in our ordinary Converſation is beyond affirmation and denial, <hi>cometh of evil.</hi> I do not think that any excuſes will be heard for that man who goes on in any known ſin, much leſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105688:13"/>in his behalf who lives in the violation of ſo plain and eaſy a Law as this which forbids common Swearing; but becauſe there are many given to this ſin, who are ready to excuſe themſelves pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently when they are admoniſh'd, and to ask your pardon, if you ſeem to be offended and grieved, and then think that they have given you reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſatisfaction, as they hope they have done the like to God, by confeſſing that truly they ought not to ſwear in this faſhion, and God forgive them for it, but yet they go on ſtill to do the ſame thing; one would think there were ſome notable Temptation to this ſin, which would go very far to extenuate the guilt of it, and which rendred the avoiding of it ſo very difficult, that all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard which could reaſonably be expected to be given to that Law of God which forbids it, is to confeſs our fault, and cry God's mercy every time we commit it; and that a good-natur'd man ought to be very well ſatisfied with the acknowledgment. I have already ſhewn, that this is a Sin which ſtands in need of an excuſe as much as any: I ſhall now ſhew, that there is none leſs capable of an excuſe, by examining what is uſually pretended for it. I never heard that any Swearer ever fancied his Oaths to be for his Health, or his Wealth; that they prolong his Life, or encreaſe his Eſtate; that they give the Wine a brisker flavour, or bring the Gameſter any good luck; that they eaſe him of his pains, or ſet off his Pleaſures. I ſuppoſe you are all ſenſible, that theſe pretences would be very ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, and truly they are not much better that follow; as,</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105688:13"/>
            <p> Firſt of all, That they are an Ornament to a man's diſcourſe; that they ſet off his language; and if they are well placed, they make a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence run the better. I ſhould have been aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to mention this excuſe, but that they ſay it goes a great way with ſome people. Now this very excuſe betrays Fantaſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Pride, and comes of a fooliſh affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be counted a Wit, which every body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt knows to be an argument of a mean and degenerate ſpirit; the reaſon why at any time Oaths and profane Talk are affected for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is, becauſe they are ſometimes obſerved to ſurprize the Hearers, which makes the profane Perſon conceit that his Wit is acknowledged, when in truth it is only the extravagance and boldneſs of his Talk that is wondred at. Folly, that is ſomething out of the road, is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly apt to provoke laughter, than a ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zal that is truly ingenious; and therefore for a man to have an Opinion of himſelf, meerly becauſe he is able to make the Company ſtare upon him, ariſeth from nothing but a mixture of Pride and Ignorance: As to this particular matter of Swearing, it is plain that an Oath ſignifies only to the affirming or denying of what is ſaid, but adds nothing to the weight of the ſenſe, or to the ſtile wherein it is expreſt; it may ſtartle a modeſt man, but it cannot pleaſe any wiſe man, becauſe it neither mends the matter, nor helps the phraſe. But is it not ſtrange, that that ſhould go for Wit, which the very baſeſt of the People can make uſe of
<pb facs="tcp:105688:14"/>with as much freedom and diſcretion, and with as good a grace as a man of the beſt quality and breeding can do? for the truth is, there is nothing required to this kind of pleaſantneſs, but to get ones forhead furniſhed with Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: which if the meaneſt Peaſant be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, he is then qualified for a good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, meerly by having a memory large enough to take in half a dozen Oaths, and a Tongue in his Head to uſe them as occaſion ſerves; which, experience ſhows, may be done without any natural Sagacity, or Rules of Art.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſometimes pretended by common Swearers, though I think but rarely, That men will not believe them without an Oath: and what is this but to confeſs, they have been ſo notoriouſly given to Lying, that no body dares truſt them upon their bare word? for a man that is known to make conſcience of ſpeaking the Truth, finds no difficulty of creating a belief of what he ſays amongſt any of his Friends, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any appeal to God. Beſides, the Oath of a common Swearer gives indeed but very little aſſurance of the truth of what he ſays; if I know a man to be afraid of an Oath, his Oath ſhall ſatisfy me beyond any other teſtimony that he can give; and upon the Oath of ſuch a man, a Court of Judicature may proceed with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; but what regard can reaſonably be had to his Oath above his ſimple and bare word, as we uſe to ſay, who is known to ſwear upon all occaſions? if he does not lie, 'tis well, but of this I have no peculiar aſſurance by his Oath,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105688:14"/>becauſe it is as ordinary with him to ſwear, as to ſpeak; and therefore in <hi>Athens,</hi> a Common Swearer's Oath was not allowed, nor accepted of in their Courts; and ſometimes the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a man of known Probity and Honour was admitted without it; this laſt ſeems to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by the wiſdom of our Laws, which ſuppoſe the Aſſeveration of a Peer to be equivalent to the Oath of another man; and therefore for another man to Swear needleſly, is to diſparage the Reputation of his Fidelity; but for a man of Honour to do ſo, is to renounce his Privilege; and for any man to do thus, is not only to bring the honeſty of his Word, but the truth of his Oath alſo into queſtion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The moſt uſual excuſe framed for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuation of this Impiety, is that of ſudden Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; thus when ſome men are a little provoked, or when they are ſurprized with ſome unexpected good Fortune, or any unlook'd-for miſadventure befals them, either their Rage or their Joy burſts out preſently into Oaths, and they pretend they cannot help it; for they have no other way to diſcharge their minds, and give vent to their Paſſions, but by Curſing and Swearing; now is not this a plain confeſſion, that they have loſt the government of themſelves, and <hi>have no rule over their own ſpirits?</hi> So common it is for men, while they are framing an excuſe for one ſin, to betray themſelves guilty of another; what greater argument can lightly be given of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent mind, than that every petty accident is able to bereave one of all conſideration, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105688:15"/>make him ceaſe to be his own man till the fit is over? And the truth is, though Paſſion be brought in to mitigate the buſineſs, yet it is plain enough, that any trifling occaſion is able to ſet theſe men a ſwearing, that make this excuſe for themſelves; when provocation is alledged to mollify this Crime, one would think it muſt ariſe from no leſs a cauſe than if he ſhould find his houſe in flames, or his friend attempting the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his bed; but upon examination, this ſame emotion and heat of ſpirit, is pleaded for the begging of your pardon, when a man ſwears upon the moſt trifling and inconſiderable occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: And what can excuſe that childiſhneſs and impotency of mind to which theſe men have thus given themſelves over? But let never ſuch extraordinary cauſes of joy, or grief, or anger, happen, it is an unmanly thing to ſet no bounds to theſe Paſſions, and they are never leſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled, than when we make ſuch undue expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of them, as Oaths and Curſes are; St. <hi>James</hi> gives us this Rule, <hi>Above all things, my brethren, ſwear not, neither by heaven, neither by the earth, nor by any other Oath, James</hi> 5.12. But the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Caſe wherein he thought this Rule was uſeful, was that of Affliction, for he had before exhorted them to whom he wrote, to <hi>take the Prophets for an example of ſuffering affliction, and of patience,</hi> and particularly recommended to them the meekneſs and patience of <hi>Job</hi> for their imitation, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11. But if they could not perfectly equal ſuch great examples as thoſe were, yet at leaſt he ſtrictly enjoins them not to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105688:15"/>tranſported ſo far into Anger and Impatience as to break forth into Oaths: <hi>But above all things, my brethren, ſwear not,</hi> but keep your ſelves within the bounds of modeſt and Chriſtian Language; and that they might ſee that he allowed them to have a ſenſe of the good and evil of this World, and was far from thinking it a Virtue to be ſtupid, and dull, and unconcerned about either the Comforts, or the Calamities of human Life; he directs them how they may convert the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which are thereby excited, to an excellent and profitable uſe; <hi>Is any man among you afflicted, let him pray; Is any merry? let him ſing Pſalms, ver.</hi> 13, 15. If any man be overtaken with worldly miſery, let him turn himſelf to more devout and earneſt Prayer, that God would ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remove his burden, or give him patience under it; if he be ſurprized with ſome new bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, let him break forth into the Praiſes of God, to whoſe Bounty and Goodneſs he ſtands obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for it. Thus to improve the excitations of joy and grief within us, is a demonſtration that our Paſſions have not overwhelmed our Reaſon and Underſtanding, but left us the free uſe of our ſelves, to do what becomes us as Men and Chriſtians; but in either caſe to laſh out into Oaths, is a plain token of an impotent mind, that hath no rule over it ſelf, but is hurried away by intemperate Paſſions, which is matter of ſo much ſhame to a reaſonable Creature, and much more to a Diſciple of Chriſt, that we ſhould bluſh to confeſs ſo much evil againſt our ſelves, as to make it the excuſe of any other Sin.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105688:16"/> 4. If Swearing be excuſed under the notion of a compliance with the cuſtom of other men who are our Friends and Companions; this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence indeed carries a ſhew of civility and kind nature; but for all that, is the ſillieſt that can readily be thought of, and the making of it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a mean and degenerate mind; for although in things of an innocent and indifferent nature 'tis commendable for men to remit of their own way and humour, and to ſuit themſelves to the cuſtoms and manners of thoſe whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with; yet to be complaiſant in all things without exception, is the way to grow as profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and vile as the Devil would wiſh any man to be; for what wickedneſs could want Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, if this pretence were once admitted? What is this but to proclaim, that a man hath loſt all ſenſe of difference between good and evil? And that he hath left off to judge all things accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own nature; that he hath no more uſe left for his Reaſon; that his Conſcience is no longer in his own keeping, and that he is now fit to herd with the Beaſts that follow the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt without diſcretion? The Laws of Truth and Goodneſs are immutable; and another man's violation of them, gives me no diſpenſation to do ſo too; I may not proſtitute my Conſcience to the Luſts of other men, who are to be governed by the Laws of God as well as I; if they call my reſolution not to provoke my Maker, an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; in this matter I were a Fool not to be tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of my own humour; in this caſe there can be no reaſon why he that is in the right, ſhould go
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105688:16"/>over to him that is wrong, unleſs he that ſets the evil example could change the nature of things, and make evil not to be evil, and ſin and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be other things than what they are.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The common way of excuſing raſh Oaths, by pleading an habit, implieth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evil of this nature that can be; for this is but to confeſs that a man is guilty of this ſin in the higheſt degree, an evil cuſtom being the heighth of wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Thus both by ſhewing what thoſe diſpoſitions are which lead to common Swearing, and by conſidering the excuſes that are uſually framed in the behalf of it, I have diſcovered the Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality thereof, and that it <hi>cometh of evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might here add the Authority of Wiſe men, who had no particular Revelation to guide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by, and yet condemned this practice, and diſſwaded all men from it; for theſe Perſons could diſcover the evil of it only by the light of Natural Reaſon, which they could not have done, if it had not been evil in its own nature. <hi>Plato</hi> wrote ſmartly againſt Swearing upon light cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; <hi>Hierocles</hi> tells us, It is a diſhonour to truth to confirm it lightly with an Oath. <hi>Epictetus</hi> gives this advice, Avoid Swearing altogether, if thou canſt; if not, as much as thou canſt. In a word, The wiſe and ſober Heathens were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of this mind, That an Oath was to be reſerved for Caſes of neceſſity; and the practice of common Swearing was not in uſe amongſt any but Stage-players and Slaves; nor do we ordinarily meet with Oaths in any of their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105688:17"/>excepting the Comedians, and ſome of their diſſolute Poets; but the grave men and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers took not the liberty themſelves, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted others from it. And this may ſerve to confirm us in the belief of its Immorality; for what ſo many wiſe men agreed in condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeems to be condemn'd as evil, by reaſons common to all men, and poſſibly ſuch as I have offered to your conſideration; ſo great a ſhame and ignominy it is to Chriſtians to allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Cuſtom ſo eaſy avoidable, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the light of Nature, however by the Authority of the Son of God, whoſe Diſciples we profeſs our ſelves to be.</p>
            <p>Thus have I finiſhed what I had to ſay upon this ſubject, having been willing to ſay all that was any way proper to oppoſe a cuſtom tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo manifeſtly to the diſhonour of our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the diſcredit of our Church, and the ſcandal of Chriſtian Society, and finally, to the ruin of Mens ſouls for ever; for without uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal obedience to the Laws of Chriſt, whereof this is one which I have been preaching to you, we cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; for which reaſon if I had choſen any other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of our Lord and Saviour to diſcourſe upon, I had been as vehement in urging you to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of that, as I have been in preſſing this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the God of mercy grant that we may walk before him blameleſs, and be holy in all manner of Converſation as becomes the followers of Jeſus; To Him with the Father and the Holy Spirit be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all honour, praiſe, and glory, now, and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
